A Guide to the Dromgoole family records, 1788-1840
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Dromgoole family records, 1788-1840
The Library of Virginia
24937
6 cu. ft. (56 volumes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Brunswick-Greensville Regional Library, 8 April 1959.
Biographical Information
Edward Dromgoole, Sr. (1751-1835) came from Ireland to Maryland in 1770. He served in various parts of Virginia as a traveling minister. Upon his marriage to Rebecca Walton (1753-1826) he settled in Brunswick County, Virginia in 1786, where he became a successful planter and merchant. He continued as an active local preacher on the Brunswick and later the Greensville circuits.
Dromgoole's children were Edward Dromgoole, Jr. (1788-1840), physician, planter, merchant, and Methodist minister of Brunswick County; Mary (d. 1835); Rebecca; Richard; and Thomas, who was also a Methodist minister. Another son, George Coke Dromgole (1797-1847), was a member of the Virginia House and Senate. He served in the U.S. House of Representatives from 1835 through 1841, and from 1843 until his death.
Family mercantile operations appear to have been directed from a store at Canaan in Brunswick County, Virginia, with branch stores designated as Belfast, Oak Hill, Pleasant Grove, and Sligoe. These place names have not been definitely located on contemporary maps.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the financial record books of the Dromgoole's stores at Belfast, Canaan, Oak Hill, Pleasant Grove, and Sligoe, Virginia. Accounts are recorded with individuals from Brunswick, Greensville, and Mecklenburg Counties, Virginia and from North Carolina. Invoice books contain names of numerous firms or individuals with whom Dromgoole placed his orders. All stores seem to have stocked a large selection of hardware, dry goods, groceries, cutlery, and china. Records of the various stores include daybooks, journals, ledgers, as well as arithmetic ciphering and exercise books of Asbury and George C. Dromgoole.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Belfast, 1813-1817
Series II: Brunswick, 1805-1818
Series III: Canaan, 1798-1840
Series IV: Oak Hill, 1810-1815
Series V: Pleasant Grove, 1832-1834
Series VI: Sligoe, 1788-1797
Series VII: Miscellaneous, 1788-1834
Contents List
- Series I: Belfast, 1813-1817., Extent: 2 volumes (1 box and on shelf).
  - Daybook (Vol. 1), 1 Nov. 1813 - 30 Sept. 1817. (Volume on shelf)
    (also contains Oak Hill Journal Vol. 27, 2 Oct. 1815 - 4 Nov. 1815)
  - Daybook (Vol. 2), Dec. 1816 - 30 Sept. 1817. (Box 1)
- Series II: Brunswick, 1805-1818., Extent: 2 volumes (1 box).
  - Daybook (Vol. 3), 14 Oct. 1815 - 24 June 1818. (Box 2)
  - Invoice book (Vol. 4), Oct. 1805 - Feb. 1812. (Box 2)
- Series III: Canaan, 1798-1840., Extent: 21 volumes (11 boxes and on shelf).
  - Daybook (Vol. 5), 1 Oct. 1798 - 16 Oct. 1799. (Box 3)
  - Daybook (Vol. 6), 1 Oct. 1799 - 30 Sept. 1800. (Box 3)
  - Daybook (Vol. 7), 1. Oct. 1800 - 30 Sept. 1802. (Box 4)
  - Daybook (Vol. 8 and 9), 1 Jan. 1805 - 27 Nov. 1806. (Box 4)
  - Daybook (Vol. 10), 8 Nov. 1817 - 30 Sept. 1819. (Box 5)
  - Daybook (Vol. 11), 1 Oct. 1819 - 30 Sept. 1820. (Box 5)
  - Daybook (Vol. 12), 1 Oct. 1821 - 29 Sept. 1823. (Box 5)
  - Daybook (Vol. 12a), 7 Oct. 1823 - 29 Sept. 1825. (Box 6)
  - Daybook (Vol. 13), 19 Apr. 1839 - 1 Sept. 1840. (Box 6)
  - Journal F (Vol. 14), 1 Oct. 1798 - 30 Sept. 1801. (Volume on shelf)
  - Journal G (Vol. 15), 1 Oct. 1801 - 29 Sept. 1804. (Volume on shelf)
  - Journal G (Vol. 16), 1 Oct. 1806 - 26 Sept. 1809. (Box 7)
  - Journal H (Vol. 16a), 2 Oct. 1809 - 26 Dec. 1828. (Box 7)
  - Journal (Vol. 17), 8 Nov. 1817 - 30 Sept. 1820. (Box 8)
  - Journal D (Vol. 18), 2 Oct. 1820 - 30 Sept. 1822. (Box 8)
  - Journal E (Vol. 19), 1 Oct. 1822 - 26 Nov. 1825. (Box 9)
  - Journal F (Vol. 20), 1 Oct. 1825 - 29 Dec. 1828. (Box 10)
  - Journal G (Vol. 21), 1 Oct. 1830 - 29 Sept. 1834. (Box 11)
  - Journal H (Vol. 22), 1 Oct. 1834 - 29 Sept. 1838. (Box 12)
  - Journal I (Vol. 23), 1 Oct. 1838 - 1 Sept. 1840. (Box 13)
- Series IV: Oak Hill, 1810-1815., Extent: 4 volumes (2 boxes and on shelf).
  - Daybook (Vol. 24), 10 Oct. 1810 - 13 Sept. 1813. (Box 13)
  - Journal A (Vol. 25), 10 Oct. 1810 - 30 Apr. 1814. (Volume on shelf)
  - Journal (Vol. 26), 2 May 1814 - 30 Sept. 1815. (Box 14)
  - Journal B (Vol. 27), 2 Oct. 1815 - 4 Nov. 1815. (Volume on shelf)
    (located with Vol. 1, Belfast daybook, 1 Nov. 1813 - 30 Sept. 1817, on shelf)
- Series V: Pleasant Grove, 1832-1834., Extent: 1 volume (1 box).
  - Daybook (Vol. 28), 5 Nov. 1832 - 5 Sept. 1834. (Box 14)
- Series VI: Sligoe, 1788-1797., Extent: 8 volumes (3 boxes and on shelf).
  - Daybook (Vol. 29), 2 Feb. 1793 - 30 Sept. 1793. (Box 15)
  - Daybook (Vol. 30), 9 Dec. 1795 - 30 Sept. 1796. (Box 15)
  - Daybook (Vol. 31), 2 Oct. 1797 - 29 Sept. 1798. (Box 15)
  - Journal (Vol. 32), 1 Oct. 1788 - 29 Sept. 1790. (Box 16)
  - Journal D (Vol. 33), 1 Oct. 1790 - 30 Apr. 1792. (Volume on shelf)
  - Journal M (Vol. 34), 1 Sept. 1792 - 30 Sept. 1793. (Box 16)
  - Journal (Vol. 35), 2 Feb. 1795 - 30 Sept. 1796. (Volume on shelf)
  - Journal (Vol. 36), 31 Oct. 1796 - 30 Sept. 1797. (Box 17)
- Series VII: Miscellaneous, 1788-1834., Extent: 19 volumes (8 boxes and on shelf).
  - Invoice book (Vol. 37), 8 Oct. 1798 - 1 Oct. 1805. (Box 17)
  - Ledger (Vol. 38), 1788 - 1790. (Box 17)
  - Ledger (Vol. 39), 1792 - 1793. (Box 18)
  - Ledger (Vol. 40), 1793, 1797 (incomplete). (Box 18)
  - Leger (Vol. 41), 1793 - 1796 (incomplete). (Box 18)
  - Ledger (Vol. 42), 1797 - 1798. (Box 19)
  - Ledger (Vol. 43), 1798 - 1801. (Volume on shelf)
  - Ledger (Vol. 43a), 1801 - 1809. (Volume on shelf)
  - Ledger A (Vol. 44), 1810-1815. (Volume on shelf)
  - Ledger B (Vol. 45), 1815 - 1817. (Volume on shelf)
  - Ledger A (Vol. 46), 1815 - 1817. (Box 19)
    (inscribed, W. H. Valentine)
  - Ledger (Vol. 47), 1817 - 1820. (Box 20)
  - Ledger D (Vol. 48), 1820 - 1822. (Box 21)
  - Ledger (Vol. 49), 1820 - 1830. (Box 21)
  - Ledger E (Vol. 50), 1822 - 1825. (Box 22)
  - Ledger F (Vol. 51), 1825 - 1830. (Box 23)
  - Ledger G (Vol. 52), 1830-1834. (Box 24)
  - Arithmetic ciphering book of Asbury Dromgoole (Vol. 53), 1810. (Box 24)
  - Arithmetic exercise book of George C. Dromgoole (Vol. 54), 1809. (Box 24)